<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6194 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6194.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7292 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7292.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7914 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7914.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8018 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8018.xml">

]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-lamps-pkcs12-pbmac1-00" ipr="trust200902"
    updates="RFC7292">
  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <title abbrev="PBMAC1 in PKCS#12">Use of Password Based Message
    Authentication Code 1 (PBMAC1) in PKCS #12 Syntax</title>

    <author fullname="Hubert Kario" initials="H." role="editor"
            surname="Kario">
      <organization>Red Hat, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Purkynova 115</street>

          <city>Brno</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>61200</code>

          <country>Czech Republic</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <email>hkario@redhat.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="5" month="October" year="2022" />

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <keyword>pbmac1, pkcs12, pbkdf2</keyword>

    <abstract>
        <t>This document specifies additions and amendments to <xref
            target="RFC7292">RFC 7292</xref>. It defines a way to use
            the Password Based Message Authentication Code 1, defined
            in <xref target="RFC8018">RFC 8018</xref>, inside the PKCS #12
            syntax. The purpose of this specification is to permit use of more
            modern PBKDFs and allow for regulatory compliance.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
        <t>The <xref target="RFC7292">PKCS #12</xref> format is widely used
        for interoperable transfer of certificate, key, and other
        miscellaneous secrets between machines, applications, browsers, etc.
        Unfortunately, the original specification mandates the use
        of a specific password based key derivation function, allowing
        only for change of the underlying message digest function.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Rationale">
        <t>Due to security concerns with PBKDF1 and much higher extensibility
        of PBMAC1, we propose the use of PBMAC1 for integrity protection
        of PKCS #12 structures. The new syntax is designed to allow legacy
        applications to still be able to decrypt the key material, even if they
        are unable to interpret the new integrity protection, provided that
        they can ignore failures in MAC verification.
        Use of the extensible PBMAC1 mechanism also allows for greater
        flexibility and alignment to different government regulations.
        </t>
        <t>As recommended methods for key protection require both encryption
        and integrity protection, we've decided to amend the PKCS #12 format
        to support different key derivation functions rather than extending the
        PKCS #5 by a new field allowing integrity protection.
        </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- This PI places the pagebreak correctly (before the section title) in the text output. -->

    <?rfc needLines="8" ?>

    <section title="Embedding PBMAC1 in PKCS #12">
        <t>The MacData structure in the PFX object is changed as follows:
        <list style="numbers">
            <t>the id-PBMAC1 object identifier is permitted as a valid type
                for the DigestAlgorithmIdentifier inside the DigestInfo object.
                If the algorithm field of the DigestAlgorithmIdentifier is
                id-PBMAC1, then the parameters field MUST be present and have
                the value consistent with PBMAC1-params</t>
            <t>if the PBMAC1 algorithm is used, the digest value of the
                DigestInfo object MUST be the result of the PBMAC1 calculation
                over the authSafe field using the PBMAC1-params parameters</t>
            <t>if the PBMAC1 algorithm is used, the macSalt value MUST be
                ignored, for backwards compatibility it SHOULD NOT be empty</t>
            <t>if the PBMAC1 algorithm is used, the iteration value MUST be
                ignored, for backwards compatibility it SHOULD have a non-zero
                positive value</t>
        </list>
        </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Recommended parameters">
        <t>To provide interoperability between different implementations,
        all implementations of this specification MUST support the PBKDF2
        key derivation function paired with SHA-256 HMAC. It's RECOMMENDED
        for implementations to support other SHA-2 based HMACs.
        Implementations MAY use other KDF methods, like the scrypt PBKDF
        <xref target="RFC7914">RFC 7914</xref>.
        </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Deprecated Algorithms">
        <t>While attacks against SHA-1 HMACs are not considered practical
            <xref target="RFC6194"/> to limit the number of algorithms needed
            for interoperatbility, implementations of this specification
            SHOULD NOT use PBKDF2 with the SHA-1 HMAC. Additionally
            the implementation MUST NOT use any other message digest functions
            with output of 160 bits or smaller.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Except for use of different key derivation functions, this document
        doesn't change how the integrity protection on PKCS #12 objects is
        computed; therefore all the original security considerations from
        <xref target="RFC7292">RFC 7292</xref> apply.
      </t>
      <t>Use of PBMAC1 and PBKDF2 is unchanged from <xref target="RFC8018">
        RFC 8018</xref>; therefore all the original security considerations
        apply.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->


    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;

      &RFC6194;

      &RFC7292;

      &RFC8018;

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

      &RFC7914;

    </references>

    <section anchor="app-additional" title="Additional Stuff">
      <t>This becomes an Appendix.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
